# **FELICIEN IHIRWE**

### Software engineering & Low-code engineering

% fihirwe.github.io

in linkedin.com/in/jean-felicien-ihirwe/

github.com/fihirwe

@ ifelicie@alumni.cmu.edu

**+39 3516148411** 

Pisa, Italy



# <u>BIO</u>

I'm Felicien, a final year Ph.D. candidate in the Department of Information Engineering, Computer Science, and Mathematics (DISIM) at the University of L'Aquila/Italy. I'm part of Intecs Solutions S.p.A's Research and Development team under the Innovation Technology Service lab (Pisa-Italy). I have a Master's degree in Electrical and Computer Engineering from Carnegie Mellon University. Despite my interest and working experience as a Software Engineer, I'm working on research areas of Model-based software engineering (MBSE), Low-code Engineering (LCE), and the Internet of Things (IoT) at the Edge/Fog/Cloud. Low-code software engineering approaches integrates the theoretical and technical research in low-code software development platforms, MBSE, cloud computing, and machine learning to automate the development of more advanced software in the domains such as system engineering, IoT and cyber-physical systems. My current work focuses on developing a robust domain-specific environment for the development, analysis and deployment of engineering IoT systems by employing low-code software engineering principles.

#### **EDUCATION**

#### P.h.D in Information Science and Engineering

Mov 2019 - Ongoing

**Q** University of L'Aquila

Interest: Low-code engineering & Domain-specific languages & IoT

#### M.Sc. in Electrical and Computer Engineering

## July 2017 - June 2019

Carnegie Mellon University

Interest: Software engineering & Machine Learning

#### **B.Sc. in Electronics and Telecommunication Engineering**

 **♀** College of Science and Technology-University of Rwanda

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

# Research Assistant/Model-based software engineer

#### **Intecs Solutions S.p.A**

m December 2019-Current

**♀** Pisa,Italy

- Computer Science applications in Low-code engineering with MDE practices for engineering IoT systems.
- Main developer of CHESSIoT framework; an MDE environment for developing, analysis and deployment of engineering IoT systems.
- Model-based safety analysis of engineering IoT systems employing Fault Tree Analysis approaches.
- Platform-specific code generators (C/Arduino/ThingML).
- AutomatIC deployment and monitoring of generated services.
   Technologies: Java, UML, EMF, Acceleo, Qvto, Xtext, ETL, Docker.

# Software Developer WYS Itd

₩ Jan 2019 - June 2019

♥ Kigali, Rwanda

- Software development with a Java-based development stack.
- System integration framework with different multipurpose consumer services.
- Reporting and software documentation.
   Technologies: Java, SpringBoot, JPA, Security, Thymlearf, JQuery and Bootstrap Docker, Postgres, MySQL

#### Co-Founder & Developer

#### TaagMind Itd

September 2018 - October 2020

- ♥ Kigali, Rwanda
- TaagMind aim is to offer Augmented & Virtual reality (AR&VR) experience to client.
- Technologies used: C#, Python, Unity3D, Node.Js, React Frameworks, SparkAR Studio.

#### Data Scientist (Internship)

#### **Rwanda Revenue Authority**

May 2018 - September 2018

- ♥ Kigali, Rwanda
- · Worked on Electronic Billing Machine (EBM) data to improve the VAT tax payment compliance and service quality.
- Developed a Machine Learning model to predict non-reporting EBM machine.
- Technologies used: Python, Data-manipulation, Jupiter-notebook, Tableau, Flask

#### Administrative Support Officer

#### **Carnegie Mellon University - Africa**

₩ Jan 2018 - May 2018

♥ Kigali, Rwanda

• General office support for various administrative functions of the organization.

## Electronics & Repair Engineer

#### **BBOXX Capital**

May 2016 - August 2017

♥ Kigali, Rwanda

- Efficiently provided a great working commitment to the company product refurbishment processes, unshipping, product quality check and deployment to the market.
- Close collaboration with the ongoing product design team to improve client's satisfactions.

#### IT & Automation officer (Internship)

#### **BRALIRWA - Part of Heineken**

May 2015 - August 2015

♥ Kigali, Rwanda

- Contributed to the design and implementation of new system wiring optimization of brewery expansion.
- Effectively identified and fixed faults which arose in company electrical and automotive network.

#### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

#### **PUBLISHED PAPERS**

**#** 2022

• "Assessing the Quality of Low-Code and MDE Platforms for Engineering IoT Systems". Felicien Ihirwe, Davide Di Ruscio, Simone Gianfranceschi, and Alfonso Pierantonio. In Proceedings of the 22nd IEEE International Conference on Software Quality, Reliability, and Security (QRS22). 12 Pages. November 2022 [Online]

#### **2021**

- "Cloud-based modeling in IoT domain: a survey, open challenges and opportunities". Felicien Ihirwe, Arsene Indamutsa, Davide Di Ruscio, Silvia Mazzini, and Alfonso Pierantonio. In the Proceedings of 2021 ACM/IEEE International Conference on Model Driven Engineering Languages and Systems Companion (MODELS 2021). October 2021 DOI: 10.1109/MODELS-C53483.2021.00018.
- "A domain specific modeling and analysis environment for complex IoT applications". Felicien Ihirwe, Davide Di Ruscio, Silvia Mazzini, and Alfonso Pierantonio. In the 7th Italian Conference on ICT for Smart Cities And Communities (I-CiTies'21). September 2021. [Online]

- "Towards an MQTT5 geo-location extension for location-aware applications". Felicien Ihirwe, Giovanni Iovino, and Davide Di Ruscio. In the 44th IEEE International Conference on Telecommunications and Signal Processing (TSP'21). DOI: 10.1109/TSP52935. 2021.9522590. July 2021 [Online]
- "Towards a modeling and analysis environment for industrial IoT systems". Felicien Ihirwe, Davide Di Ruscio, Silvia Mazzini, and Alfonso Pierantonio. In the International workshop on MDE for Smart IoT Systems co-located with Software Technologies: Applications and Foundations (MESS@STAF21) conferences. June 2021. [Online - DOI]
- "Model-based Analysis Support for Dependable Complex Systems in CHESS". Alberto Debiasi, Felicien Ihirwe, Pierluigi Pierini, Silvia Mazzini, and Stefano Tonetta. In Proceedings of the 9th International Conference on Model-Driven Engineering and Software Development - MODELSWARD'21. ISBN 978-989-758-487-9; ISSN 2184-4348, pages 262-269. DOI: 10.5220/0010269702620269. February 2021 [Online]

**#** 2020

• "Low-code Engineering for the Internet of things: A state of research". Felicien Ihirwe, Davide Di Ruscio, Silvia Mazzini, Pierluigi Pierini, and Alfonso Pierantonio. In Proceedings of the 23rd ACM/IEEE International Conference on Model Driven Engineering Languages and Systems: Companion Proceedings (MODELS'20). Article No.: 74 Pages 1–8 DOI:10.1145/3417990.3420208. October 2020 [Online]

#### **TEACHING EXPERIENCE**

#### Carnegie Mellon University

# Fall 2018

**♥** Kigali-Rwanda

• Graduate Teaching Assistant: 04-330 Foundations of Software Engineering and Problem Solving.

🛗 July-Aug 2018, 2019, 2021 and 2022

**♥** Kigali-Rwanda

• Graduate Teaching Assistant: Introduction to Linux-Java programming orientation course.

#### The African Centre of Excellence in Data Science (ACEDS)

## Fall 2019 and 2020

**♀** Remote

• Graduate Teaching Assistant: DSC6231 Computer Systems and Data Analytics.

#### High school teaching (ACEC)

## February 2012 - June 2015

• Teacher: Mathematics and Physics for Advanced level studies.

#### PAPER REVIEWS CONTRIBUTIONS

External Reviewer: Journal of Object Technology (JOT)
 Topics: MDE, IoT, communication protocols, QoS.

• Invited Reviewer: IET Software journal

**Topics:** IoT and Machine learning applications, edge computing, communication protocols.

Shadow Program Committee: Mining Software Repositories conference (MSR'21)
 Topics: Mining android apps software repositories.

#### **VOLUNTEER**

- Student Volunteer: The 49th ACM SIGPLAN Symposium on Principles of Programming Languages (POPL 2022). 

  Sun 16 Sat 22 January 2022
- Student Volunteer: The 36th IEEE/ACM Int. Conf. on Automated Software Engineering (ASE 2021). 🛗 Sun 14 Sat 20 November 2021
- Student Volunteer: ACM / IEEE 24rd Int. Conf. on Model Driven Engineering Languages and Systems (MODELS'21) ## 10-15 October 2021
- Student Volunteer: 25th ACM International Systems and Software Product Line Conference (SPLC 2021) Sept 6-11, 2021
- Vice-president: Energy and embedded system community Carnegie Mellon university-Africa 🛗 Dec 2017-Feb 2019

#### **SPEAKER AT CONFERENCES**

- "A domain specific modeling and analysis environment for complex IoT applications" 7th" at the Italian Conference on ICT for Smart Cities and Communities (I-CITIES 2021) (Speaker) ## 22-24 September, 2021
- "Towards an MQTT5 geo-location extension for location-aware applications" at the 44th IEEE International Conference on Telecommunications and Signal Processing (TSP'21) (Speaker) ## July 26-28, 2021.
- "Towards a modeling and analysis environment for industrial IoT systems" at Software Technologies: Applications and Foundations conferences (MESS@STAF21'21) (Speaker) # 21-25 June 2021.

# **PROJECTS**

#### Lowcomote (EU H2020-ITN n. 813884)

Lowcomote aims to train a generation of professionals in the design, development and operation of new LCDPs, that overcome the limitations above, by being scalable (i.e., supporting the development of large-scale applications, and using artefacts coming from a large number of users), open (i.e., based on interoperable and exchangeable programming models and standards), and heterogeneous (i.e., able to integrate with models coming from different engineering disciplines).

# TECHNICAL SKILLS[\*:BASIC]

Programming Language

Java, Python (Flask), Arduino, Node.js\*, SQL, C/C++, Assembly\*, MATLAB, EMF/UML/SysML, ETL, Acceleo, Xtext/Xtend\*/Qvto\*

**SWD Framework** 

SpringMVC, SpringBoot, Flask, Django, PyTorch, Keras\*, Unity3D

**Data Science** 

Python/Matlab, Appplied Machine Learning, Deep learning

Front-end

JQuery, BootStrap, Thymeleaf, React360\*, AngularJS\*

Deployment

Docker(DockerFile, Docker Compose), Kubernetes\*

Editor

Eclipse, IntelliJ IDEA, VS Code, Sublime, Vi

Linux

**Linux Administration, Bash Scripting** 

OS

MacOS, Linux (Ubuntu, Kali), Windows

Database

MySQL, Postgres, MongoDB\*

Source Control

Git, SVN

Languages

English, French, Italian\*, Kinyarwanda, Kiswahili\*

**Driving Licence** 

B(EU)

#### **INTEREST**

Software Development Engineer Research Scientist Post-doctoral research Model-based system engineer Java Developer Embedded System developer



# **ACADEMIC REFERENCES**

Davide Di Ruscio Associate Professor, Department of Engineering and Information Sciences and Mathematics

University of L'Aquila

Email: davide.diruscio@univaq.it

https://people.disim.univaq.it/diruscio/

Alfonso Pierantonio Professor, Department of Engineering and Information Sciences and Mathematics

University of L'Aquila

Email: alfonso.pierantonio@univaq.it

% https://www.disim.univaq.it/AlfonsoPierantonio

Simone Gianfranceschi CTO, Head of ITS Lab

Intecs Solutions S.p.A

Email: simone.gianfranceschi@intecs.it

% LinkedIn